Dennis Nolan Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Dennis Nolan Papers.
circa 1976-1994.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Nolan, Dennis.
10.5 linear feet.
Children's book author and illustrator. Since 1986, Nolan has been the coordinator of illustration in the Hartford Art School.
MSS19940010
Biography
Dennis Nolan was born 19 October 1945, in San Francisco, CA, the son of Arthur Thomas (an opera singer) and Helen (Fortier) Nolan. He attended College of San Mateo (1963-1965), and San Jose State College (now University, B.A., 1967, M.A., 1968). Nolan began his career as a graphic artist at the San Mateo County Library (Belmont, CA, 1970-1977) and then moved on as an art instructor at Canada Junior College (Redwood City, CA, 1979-1986), San Jose State University (1983-1986) and at the College of San Mateo (1982-1986). Since 1986, Nolan has been the coordinator of illustration in the Hartford Art School in addition to illustrating many children's books. His work has received the following awards:
The Joy of Chickens,
Outstanding Science Book Award, National Science Teachers Association, 1981.
Step into the Night,
Outstanding Science Book Award, National Science Teachers Association, 1987
The Castle Builder,
Pick of the List, American Booksellers, 1987.
Top Twelve Books, 1987.
Christian Science Monitor, 1987.
Prix de Zephyr, French Librarian Award, 1988.
Step into the Night,
Parents Choice Magazine Top 15 Books, 1988.
Commonwealth Club of California award, 1988.
Legend of the White Doe,
Notable Social Studies Books selection, 1988.
Dinosaur Dream. Monster Bubbles: A Counting Book,
Golden Kite Picture Book Honor, 1990.
Junior Literary Guild selection.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials relating to twenty-two books. Mr. Nolan has either written, illustrated or contributed to the design of all of the books represented in the collection. Materials include manuscripts, book plans, revisions, drafts, sketches, some original drawings, dummies, proofs, paste ups, and production proofs (folded and gathered). There is very little finished artwork in the collection (identified as illustrations rather than sketches). The only book that came with the collection is Max's Box, which has been removed and catalogued.
Several books changed titles during the creation process. These materials are labeled according to the working title at the time of creation but are filed under the book's final title.
“Castle” The Castle Builder
“It's a Big Napping World” No Nap for Benjamin Badger
“Krysia's First Christmas in America” An Ellis Island Christmas
“Lost in Time” Dinosaur Dream
“No Nap for Me” No Nap for Benjamin Badger
“When the Mockingbird Sings” Mockingbird Morning
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Writings by the Author: for Children; Author and Illustrator
Big Pig (picture book), Prentice-Hall, 1976.
Alphabrutes (picture book), Prentice-Hall, 1977.
Monster Bubbles: A Counting Book (picture book), Prentice-Hall, 1976.
Wizard McBean and His Flying Machine (picture book), Prentice-Hall, 1977.
Witch Bazooza (picture book), Prentice-Hall, 1979.
The Joy of Chickens (nonfiction), Prentice-Hall, 1981.
The Castle Builder (picture book), Macmillan, 1987.
Wolf Child (picture book), Macmillan, 1989.
Dinosaur Dream (picture book), Macmillan, 1990.
(Reteller) Androcles and the Lion, Harcourt, 1997.
Illustrator
Charles Keller (compiler). Llama Beans, Prentice-Hall, 1979.
Bill Nygren. Gnomes Color and Story Album, Troubador Press, 1980.
Karen Schiller. Bears Color and Story Album, Troubador Press, 1982.
William Hooks. A Flight of Dazzle Angels, Macmillan, 1988.
William Hooks. The Legend of the White Doe, Macmillan, 1988.
Joanne Ryder. Step into the Night, Four Winds, 1988.
Joanne Ryder. Mockingbird Morning, Four Winds, 1989.
Jane Yolen. Dove Isabeau, Harcourt, 1989.
Nancy Carlstrom. Heather Hiding, Macmillan, 1990.
Joanne Ryder. Under Your Feet, Four Winds, 1990.
Cynthia DeFelice. Weasel, Macmillan, 1990 (?).
Jane Yolen. Wings, Harcourt, 1991.
Nancy Carlstrom. No Nap for Benjamin Badger, Macmillan, 1991.
Ann Tompert. Savina, the Gypsy Dancer, Macmillan, 1991.
Maxinne Rhea Leighton. An Ellis Island Christmas, Viking, 1992.
Kristen Avery. Max's Box, Scott Forsman, 1993.
T. H. White. The Sword in the Stone, Philomel Books, 1993.
Diane Stanley. The Gentleman and the Kitchen Maid, Dial, 1994.
Bruce Coville, reteller, William Shakespeare's A Midsummer Night's Dream, Dial, 1995.
Lauren A. Mills. Fairy Wings: A Story, Little, Brown, 1995.
Lauren A. Mills. The Dog Prince, Little, Brown, 1996.
For Adults; Illustrator
Jim Barrett and others, editors, “Sunset” Homeowner's Guide to Wood Stoves, Lane, 1979.
Source: Contemporary Authors Online. The Gale Group, 2000.
Periodicals
Booklist, April 15, 1976, p. 1192; February 15, 1978, p. 1010; December 1, 1989, p. 750; December 15, 1989, p. 834; March 15, 1990, p. 1443; October 15, 1990, p. 439; November 1, 1991, p. 330; January 15, 1994, p. 939; November 1, 1995, p. 478.
Kirkus Reviews, March 1, 1976, p. 253; January 15, 1977, p. 43; January 1, 1978, p. 1; August 15, 1989, p. 1248; October 1, 1989, p. 1483; February 15, 1990, p. 273; October 1, 1991, p. 1293.
Los Angeles Times Book Review, November 25, 1990, p. 18; December 16, 1990, p. 9.
Newsweek, December 3, 1990, p. 64.
Publishers Weekly., March 15, 1976, p. 57; January 17, 1977, p. 82; December 19, 1980, p. 52, August 14, 1987, p. 103; January 20, 1989, p. 147; July 28, 1989, p. 221; February 9, 1990, p. 60; October 26, 1990, p. 67; September 20, 1991, p. 132; November 22, 1993, p. 63; November 6, 1995, p. 94.
School Library Journal, April, 1976, p. 62; May, 1977, p. 54; February, 1978, p. 49; January, 1980, p. 60; January, 1988, p. 68; July, 1989, p. 75; December, 1989, p. 102; April, 1990, p. 110; July, 1990, p. 79; November, 1990, p. 96; August, 1994, p. 146; January, 1996, p. 90.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American 20th century.; Children's literature--Illustrations.; Children's literature--Connecticut authors.; Children's literature--Connecticut illustrators.; Illustrated children's books.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Artwork.; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Books.
Occupations:
Illustrator.; Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Mr. Nolan in 1994.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Files, undated, 1989, 1992
  - Class materials, undated, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Original drawing submitted for Bookfair poster, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
- Series II: Books, circa 1976-1994
  - Big Pig, 1976
    - Printer's proof (Box OS:, Folder 123)
  - The Castle Builder, 1987 [Dodd Call No. CLC C75]
    - Book plan (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Dummy (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Sketches (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 95)
    - Revisions (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Paste up (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Illustrations—Ink drawings (from book, text on back) (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Galleys (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Jacket proof (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Exhibit text (Box 4:, Folder 96)
    - Publicity (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Dinosaur Dream, 1990
    - Book plan (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - “Lost in Time” Manuscript (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - Dummy (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - “Lost in Time” Drafts (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - Drafts (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - Sketches (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - Sketches (Box 5:, Folder 126)
    - Time Chart (Box 5:, Folder 127)
    - Revisions (Box 2:, Folder 38)
    - Paste up (Box 2:, Folder 39)
    - Galleys (Box 2:, Folder 40)
    - Jacket with text overlay (Box 2:, Folder 41)
    - Jacket proof (Box 7:, Folder 119)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 2:, Folder 42)
    - Printer's proof (Box OS:, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence and notes, undated, 1989-1990 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
    - Research (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Dove Isabeau, Jane Yolen, 1989 [Dodd Call No. CLC C158]
    - Book plan (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Manuscript (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Sketches (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 118)
    - Jacket sketch and title page (Box 5:, Folder 100)
    - Color illustration (Box 5:, Folder 101)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Photograph (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - An Ellis Island Christmas, Maxinne Rhea Leighton, 1992
    - Book plan (Box 3:, Folder 73)
    - “Krysia's First Christmas in America” manuscript (Box 3:, Folder 74)
    - Dummy (Box 3:, Folder 75)
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 76)
    - Revisions (Box 3:, Folder 77)
    - Paste up (Box 3:, Folder 78)
    - Galleys (Box 3:, Folder 79)
    - Jacket proof with text overlay (Box 6:, Folder 115)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 3:, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1990-1992 (Box 3:, Folder 81)
    - Research materials (Box 3:, Folder 82)
  - Flight of Dazzle Angels, William Hooks, 1988
    - Jacket proof (Box 1:, Folder 125)
  - The Gentleman and the Kitchen Maid, Diane Stanley, 1994
    - Book plan (Box 3:, Folder 87)
    - Dummy (Box 3:, Folder 88)
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 89)
    - Sketches (Box 7:, Folder 120)
    - Revisions (Box 3:, Folder 90)
    - Paste up with sketch overlays, pp. 4-17 and text galley (Box 7:, Folder 121)
    - Paste up with sketch overlays, pp. 18-32 (Box 7:, Folder 122)
    - Palette (Box 3:, Folder 91)
    - Color illustration (Box 6:, Folder 116)
    - Author Biography (Box 3:, Folder 92)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1991-1993 (Box 3:, Folder 93)
  - Heather Hiding, Nancy Carlstrom, 1990 [Dodd Call No. CLC B83]
    - Proofs and correspondence, 1989 (Box 5:, Folder 106)
  - The Legend of the White Doe, William Hooks, 1988 [Dodd Call No. CLC C42]
    - Book plan (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Dummy (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 97)
  - Llama Beans, Charles Keller (compiler), 1979
    - Illustration with overlay (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Max's Box, Kristen Avery, 1993 [Dodd Call No. WPZ 156]
    - B & W illustrations with overlays, pp. 1-8 (Box 3:, Folder 83)
    - Color illustrations (Box 3:, Folder 84)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 3:, Folder 85)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 3:, Folder 86)
  - Mockingbird Morning, Joanne Ryder, 1989
    - Dummy (2) (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Monster Bubbles: A Counting Book, 1976
    - Printer's proof (Box OS:, Folder 123)
  - No Nap for Benjamin Badger, Nancy Carlstrom, 1991
    - Book plan (Box 3:, Folder 57)
    - Text (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - Revisions (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 60)
    - Paste up (Box 3:, Folder 61)
    - Color illustrations, pp. 1, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 28 (Box 3:, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
  - “Ogre”, 2002
    - Print (2 copies, 14/75, 15/75) (Box OS:, Folder 123)
  - Savina, the Gypsy Dancer, Ann Tompert, 1991
    - Manuscript (Box 3:, Folder 64)
    - Book plan (Box 5:, Folder 108)
    - Dummy (Box 3:, Folder 65)
    - Sketches (Box 3:, Folder 66)
    - Paste up (2) (Box 3:, Folder 67)
    - Galleys (Box 5:, Folder 128)
    - Color proof (Box 3:, Folder 68)
    - Jacket proof with text overlay (Box 5:, Folder 109)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 5:, Folder 110)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
  - Step into the Night, Joanne Ryder, 1988
    - Book plan (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Text (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Dummy (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Sketches (Box 4:, Folder 98)
    - Color proofs (Box 4:, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Under Your Feet, Joanne Ryder, 1990
    - Book plan (Box 2:, Folder 45)
    - Manuscript (Box 2:, Folder 46)
    - Dummy (Box 2:, Folder 47)
    - Sketches (Box 2:, Folder 48)
    - Revisions (Box 2:, Folder 49)
    - Text proof (Box 2:, Folder 50)
    - Galleys (Box 2:, Folder 51)
    - Proofs (Box 5:, Folder 107)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 2:, Folder 52)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 2:, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
    - Research material (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Weasel, Cynthia DeFelice, 1990(?)
    - Jacket proof and correspondence, 1990 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Wings, Jane Yolen, [Dodd Call No. CLC C1845], 1991
    - Book plan (Box 3:, Folder 70)
    - Draft (Box 3:, Folder 71)
    - Sketches (Box 6:, Folder 111)
    - Matted sketch (Box OS:, Folder 123)
    - Jacket design (Box 6:, Folder 112)
    - Galleys (Box 6:, Folder 113)
    - Jacket proof (Box 6:, Folder 114)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 3:, Folder 72)
  - Witch Bazooza, 1979
    - Dummy (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Paste up (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Pen and ink illustrations, pp. Cover, 2-5. 18-19 (Box 7:, Folder 117)
  - Wizard McBean and His Flying Machine, 1977
    - Dummy (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Pen and ink illustration, p. 20 (Box 4:, Folder 94)
    - Printer's proof (Box OS:, Folder 123)
  - Wolf Child, 1989 [Dodd Call No. CLC C161]
    - Revisions (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Sketches (Box 5:, Folder 102)
    - Galleys (Box 5:, Folder 103)
    - Color illustrations (photographs (Box 5:, Folder 104)
    - Production proof (f & g) (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Jacket proof (Box 5:, Folder 105)